Hector Bahamonde, PhD

Instituto de Ciencias Sociales cp (CL): +56-9-4-597-4203
Universidad de O'Higgins cp (US): +1(504) 941-9131
Chile e: hector.bahamonde@uoh.cl
w: www.HectorBahamonde.com

CV last updated: May 3, 2019. Download latest CV here.

Bio

Dr. Hector Bahamonde, an Assistant Professor of Political Science, has a successful academic career in Chile. He earned his PhD in the United States, where he also received a post-doctoral fellow too. Now, being 34 years old, he's trying to relocate to Germany, get a non-academic job, and make use of his methodological training outside academia. Married to a German woman, both want to improve their work/life balance, and spend more time with Tobias (2 years-old) and Olimpia (1 year-old).

Education

Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey-New Brunswick

Ph.D. Political Science, September 2012–May 2017.

Dissertation: "State Capacities in Latin America: Structural Transformations, Elite Competition, and Fiscal Development (1850-2010)."

Committee: Robert Kaufman (chair), Daniel Kelemen, Douglas Blair, Paul Poast (University of Chicago).

Fields: Comparative Politics and Quantitative Methodology.

Catholic University of Chile-Santiago.

B.A. Political Science, 2005–2009.

Dissertation

My dissertation argues that sectoral economic conflicts fostered state-building in Latin America. Using fine-grained historical case study comparisons, sectoral outputs from 1900 to the present, panel data and time-series econometric techniques, and a novel earthquake dataset (to measure state capacities), I find that industrial expansion altered the post-colonial political balance, thus putting heavy pressures for the implementation of tax institutions. In turn, fiscal expansion fostered both political development and economic growth.

Employment

Universidad de O'Higgins, Rancagua, Chile

Assistant Professor (tenure-track), July 2018-

Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, United States

Post-Doctoral Fellow, Center for Inter-American Policy & Research (CIPR), 2017 - June 2018

Hector Bahamonde, PhD 2

Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ, United States

Teaching Assistant, 2014-2017

Skills

Data-Oriented and Computational Social Scientist

Trained as an academic, I have deep understanding and experience in applied social research. In particular, I'm passionate about working with big datasets, causal inference (lab experiments), quasi-experiments (matching for observational studies) and programming (R and Stata). You can check my coding expertise in my GitHub.

Interpersonal

I have considerable experience as an independent critical person, used to work under pressure, and goal-oriented. Not only I have good writing/analytical skills, but also excellent interpersonal relationships. Having both excellent leadership skills, and willingness to collaborate with others, make me an ideal candidate to take different roles, for instance in different projects, in the same institution. Finally, I have vast experience conducting data/statistical analyses, IRB applications (for my own experiments), and grant writing.

Languages

English, Spanish (native).

Software

R, Stata, LATEX.

Certified Methods Proficiency

Time Series I (ICPSR), Introduction to Bayesian Analysis (ICPSR), Time Series II (ICPSR), Advanced MLE - Panel Data (ICPSR), Experimental Political Science (RU), Advanced Research in Political Economy (RU), Formal Modeling I (Princeton), Advanced Econometrics (RU, Economics), Introduction to Game Theory (ICPSR), Regression III: Advanced Methods (ICPSR), Measurement, Scaling and Dimensional Analysis (ICPSR), Causal Inference for the Social Sciences (ICPSR), Regression Analysis (RU, Statistics), Maximum Likelihood Estimation for GLMs (RU).

Research

Please note, every paper employs different sophisticated—still applied—econometric techniques.

Peer-Reviewed Articles

- Bahamonde, H. (2018). Aiming Right at You: Group versus Individual Clientelistic Targeting in Brazil. *Journal of Politics in Latin America*, 10(2), pp. 41-76.
- Bahamonde, H. (2011). El Secreto de mi Éxito: Parte II. Los Caminos a Valparaíso en 2009. Revista de Ciencia Política, 31(2), pp. 285-310. With Pilar Giannini, Juan Pablo Luna, Rodolfo López, Martín Ordoñez and Gonzalo Recart.

Hector Bahamonde, PhD 3

Work in Progress

• Income Taxation and State Capacity in Chile: Measuring Institutional Development Using Historical Earthquake Data, *under review, Comparative Politics*. Lead paper.

- Still for Sale: The Micro-Dynamics of Vote-Selling in the United States, Evidence From a List and Conjoint Experiments, *under review*, Electoral Studies.
- Sectoral Origins of Income Taxation: Industrial Development in Latin America, and The Case of Chile (1900-2010), *in preparation*.
- Structural Transformations and State Institutions in Latin America, 1900-2010, in preparation.
- Testing the Online Model of Candidate Evaluation in a More Realistic Environment, *in preparation*. With Richard Lau (Rutgers) and Mona Kleinberg (UMass Lowell).
- Inclusive Institutions, Unequal Outcomes: Democracy, State Infrastructural Power, and Inequality 1970-2015, *submitted*. With Mart Trasberg (Tulane).

Book Reviews in Peer-Reviewed Journals (Invited)

• Inés Durán Matute. "Indigenous Peoples and the Geographies of Power: Mezcala's Narratives of Neoliberal Governance" (Routledge). *Journal of Iberian and Latin American Research*.

Chapters

• ¿Estable Pero Sin Raíces? Los Partidos Políticos Chilenos en la Opinión Pública, in *Cultura Política de la Democracia en Chile, Ch. IX, LAPOP Country Report, 2010.* With Juan Pablo Luna, Germán Bidegain, Roody Reserve and Giancarlo Visconti.

Career Objective

I want to help institutions (big or small) to reach their goals by incorporating my academic experience. By bringing my analytical skills, and excellent interpersonal relationships, I am interested in both leading teams and collaborating with others. My ideal institution lets its employees be innovative, goal-oriented and creative. I have immediate availability, and I'm ready to relocate tomorrow.